A Guide to the Westmoreland County (Va.) Records, 1693-1959
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Westmoreland County (Va.) Records, 1693-1959
Library of Virginia
0007326996, 1042833-1176643 circa
53 boxes and volumes
Westmoreland County (Va.) Circuit Court
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
A portion of these records came to the Library of Virginia in shipments of court papers from Westmoreland County under the accession numbers 33162f, 33503, 34602, 41894 and 41897.
Historical Information
Westmoreland County was named for the English county. It was formed from Northumberland County in 1653. The county seat is Montross.
Scope and Content
Westmoreland County (Va.) Records, 1693-1959, includes miscellaneous records from the following series: Board of Supervisors Records; Bonds,Commissions,Oaths; Court Records; Election Records; Fiduciary Records; Land Records; Miscellaneous Records; Military and Pension Records; Public Buildings and Grounds; Road and Bridge Records; School Records; Tax and Fiscal Records; Wills.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Material
Additional Westmoreland County Records can be found on microfilm at the Library of Virginia. Consult "A Guide to Virginia County and City Records on Microfilm."
See the Lost Records Localities Digital Collection available at Virginia Memory.
Index Terms
Corporate Names:
Westmoreland County (Va.) Circuit Court.
Subjects:
Public records--Virginia--Westmoreland County.
Genre and Form Terms:
Local government records--Virginia--Westmoreland County.
Contents List
- Records, 1693-1832:
  Court Records, Fiduciary Records, Tax and Fiscal Records, and Wills.
- Court Records; Tax and Fiscal Records; Fiduciary Records, 1795-1804:
  Court Records: Executions; Tax and Fiscal Records: List of Insolvents; Levy Papers; Fiduciary Records; Inventories and Accounts; Administrator's Accounts
- Land Records; Miscellaneous Records; Fiduciary Records, 1772-1920:
  Deeds, affidavits, mechanics' liens, guardian bonds, powers of attorney
- Miscellaneous Records; Land Records; Court Records; Road and Bridge Records; Fiduciary Records; Tax and Fiscal Records, 1779-1959:
  Crow and fox scalp certificates, abstracts of title Colonial Beach School; Judgments, Commonwealth Causes; Road Petitions; Guardian, Administrator and Executor Bonds; Sales of delinquent lands
- Commissioner of Accounts Papers; Executor's and Administrator's Acounts, 1836-1843
- Index to Deeds and Wills, undated
- Conditional Sales; Record of Capitation Tax Received by Clerk, 1881-1914
- Liber (Deeds and Wills), 1747-1753
- Deeds and Orders, 1795-1797
- Bonds; Liquor Licenses, 1904-1914
  Bonds,Oaths,Commissions: Bonds (Administrators, Guardians, Executors, Officials, Chancery Commissioners); Tax and Fiscal Records: Liquor Licenses
- School Records; Court Records; Election Records, 1846-1861:
  School Records: School Commissioners Reports, 1846-1861; Court Records: Summons to answer suggestions filed, 1856-1858; Election Records, 1850s. Accession 41894. Unprocessed.
- Bonds,Commissions,Oaths; Tax and Fiscal Records; Land Records, 1820-1908 circa:
  Bonds,Commissions,Oaths: appointments and qualifications of county officers before military officer; oaths of allegeiance, 1869-1870; Tax and Fiscal Records: pedlars receipts, 1820s-1850s; Land Records: Oyster Inspector Reports, 1907-1908; deed of trust appointments, substitutions, resignations in re: Colonial Beach Improvement Company, 1887. Accession 41894. Unprocessed
- Records, 1861-1909:
  Board of Supervisors Records; Election Records; Birth Records; Road and Bridge Records; Accession 41897.
- Bonds, Commissions, Oaths; Court Records; Fiduciary Records, 1790-1924:
  Bonds,Oaths,Commissions: officials' bonds, appointments and resignations (constable, sheriff, tobacco inspector, overseer of poor, tavern, surveyor, clerks, superintendent of schools, treasurer, coroner, justice of peace, etc.), militia appointments and resignations, apprentice indentures/bonds, etc., 1897-1924; Court Records: Injunction Bonds, 1802-1824; Fiduciary Records: Adminstrators and Executors Bonds, 1790s-early 1800s; 1872-1874. Unprocessed.
- Military and Pension Records Records; Public Buildings and Grounds, 1806-1913:
  Military and Pension Records: pension papers (Revolutionary War, War of 1812, Civil War), 1806-1913, Lists of indigent families of soldiers, 1861-1865, militia fines and exemptions, 1861-1864, letter in re: military bounty land, 1816, public service claim, 1821, petition to make Civil War muster rolls official records, 1907) Public Buildings and Grounds: Architectural Drawings and Plans: clerk's office, 1822-1900, courthouse, 1824-1848, jail, 1811-1832, jail inspectors reports, 1810-1912, undated, portrait of Lord Chatham, 1821-1847, painting of George Washington, 1902, stone for Washington Monument in D.C., 1852, shade trees planted in public square, 1905, petition for a bell, undated.
- Records, 1783-1912 circa:
  Justice of the Peace Records, 1868; Election Records, 1797-1912 circa; Court Records: dockets, orders setting court dates, writs of ad quod damnum, 1783-1856; Board of Supervisors Records, 1873-1910, undated; Sheriff's Records, 1789-1822; School Records, 1873-1877, undated. Unprocessed.
- Records, 1762-1850:
  Military and Pension Records: Military Discharge of Charles Poore, 1762; Fiduciary Records: Inventory of James Degges, 1778, Inventory of James Washington, 1782, Guardian settlement of Elijah Moore, 1787; Road and Bridge Rcords: Report of road petition, 1780; Tax and Fiscal Records: Slave Patrol Accounts, 1780; Land Records: Survey and division of the estate of Willoughby Newton, 1823, 1846; Court Records: Exhibits and bonds, 1784-1850. Accession numbers 33162f, 33503, 34602
- Fiduciary Records and Wills, 1700-1912 circa
  Box 1 includes Will of Richard Lee (1795); lists of slaves emancipated by Robert Carter (1790s)
- Coroner's appointment; slave patrol commissions and accounts, 1776-1857
  Bonds,Oaths,Commissions: Coroner's Appointment, 1851; Slave patrol commissions, 1812-1857; Tax and Fiscal Records: Slave patrol accounts submitted for payment, 1776-1850